Guide to the George Platt Lynes Scrapbooks
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Platt Lynes scrapbooks.
1900-1955
YCAL MSS 139
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.78
(6 boxes)
Two scrapbooks, with loose pages and items, containing clippings, original photographic prints (by Lynes and others, including PAJAMA and Brassai), postcards, and reproductions of artworks. These volumes document Lynes's focus on photographic design elements and his developing aesthetic in his early years. Among the subjects represented are: Royal families; athletes; popular musical and film performers (with numerous images of Johnny Weismuller and Marlene Dietrich); nude models; Pavel Tchelitchew paintings and set designs; high fashion models; and humorous photographs from magazines. Ten of the loose pages feature contact prints of Lynes and his friends and family, including: Paul Cadmus; Katharine Anne Porter; Barbara and Lloyd Wescott; Adelaide Sparkman Lynes; Somerset Maugham; Jared French; Monroe Wheeler; and Glenway Wescott. Another loose page contains 26 prints of individuals posed as part of Max Ewing's "Carnival in Venice" series.
Lynes, George Platt, 1907-1955
Ewing, Max
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bernard Perlin, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Additional George Platt Lynes material can be found in the Glenway Wescott Papers [YCAL MSS 134], the Monroe Wheeler Papers [YCAL MSS 136], and George Platt Lynes Diaries and Memorabilia [YCAL MSS 147]. Max Ewing's "Carnival in Venice" photo albums are classified under the call number: Za EW55 +G1 5
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm available
GEORGE PLATT LYNES (1907-1955)
George Platt Lynes was born on April 15, 1907 to Joseph Russell and Adelaide Sparkman Lynes in East Orange, New Jersey. He attended the Berkshire School, where Lincoln Kirstein was among his classmates. Considered inadequately prepared for college, George was sent to Paris, in the care of family cousins, Kate and Walter Hardy, with the goal of improving his basic prepatory subjects. In the heady milieu of literary Paris, he made the acquaintance of Réne Crevel and Gertrude Stein, with whom he began a decade-long correspondence. (see: YCAL MSS 76, Box 115, folder 2406 and YCAL MSS 77, Box 10, folder 136a).
Lynes eventually entered Yale University in the Fall of 1926, though he attended for only a single semester. A move to New York allowed Lynes to further his contact with the literary world he had been introduced to in Paris In January, 1927, he met the publisher Monroe Wheeler and his partner, the writer, Glenway Wescott. Over the next fifteen years, Lynes' emotional life centered around Wheeler and Wescott, with whom he maintained a succession of households in France and the United States. His search for a metier saw him explore writing and bookselling before he eventually found his aesthetic through the facility of the camera. His first informal portraits were done in the late 1920s, but soon he found himself an official society photographer, contributing to significant museum shows, magazines, and having his own one-man exhibitions. He became well-known for his fashion photography and eventually was made the head of Vogue magazine's West Coast studio in Los Angeles in 1946, where he moved following several years of emotional upheaval in his personal life, which included his break from Wescott and Wheeler.
Lynes returned to New York in 1948, but found he was no longer in demand for his commercial fashion work. Instead, he focused on his private interests, male nudes, and documenting productions of the New York City Ballet. His change of fortune, which included a bankruptcy filing in the early 1950s, ended with a diagnosis of lung cancer. He died in New York City on December 6, 1955.
Scope and Contents
The George Platt Lynes Scrapbooks consist of two volumes along with several loose leaves. Though they have been largely dismantled for preservation and storage reasons, the materials have been cataloged to reflect their original organization. The scrapbooks are stored in three oversize boxes which contain the original leaves and two standard archival boxes, which hold items that were removed. The material, though mostly undated, spans the years 1900-1955, and is arranged into two series, I. Scrapbooks, and II. Separated Items: Photographs and Colored Images.
The scrapbooks present a view of images that influenced Lynes as a photographer, coupled with examples of his own work, culled mostly from fashion magazines. They also include along with articles and images documenting the work of his friends, such as Pavel Tchelitchew and Cecil Beaton. As well, many items were pasted in the scrapbooks for their humorous and cultural appeal. High fashion models appear side-by-side with monkeys, elephants, and decapitated heads. European royalty coexist with movie stars such as Marlene Dietrich, Greta Garbo, and Johnny Weismuller. Other recurring subjects include examples of extravagant interior decoration, postcards featuring scenes of native peoples of North Africa, and photographs of famous writers, musicians and singers.
Lynes' interest in the nude is quite evident in these volumes. Along with a number of clippings of nude men and women in various demuere poses are a group of photographic prints of young men and girls, and sheets with multiple shots of muscular men and women striking artistic attitudes. These include one sheet featuring the Ritter brothers.
Several of the postcards removed from the scrapbook pages revealed messages on the reverse sides, including cards from Tonio Selwart and Max Ewing. Other photographic images include: dancers of the Folies Bergères; Johnny Weismuller posing as Tarzan; a group of shots of men playing water polo; a large group of set and costume illustrations most likely by Pavel Tchelitchew; a portrait of Ambrose Vollard by Brassai; a portrait of a woman wearing a costume made of sealife, possibly after Dali; and one print that is annotated as being by Lynes,
The loose scrapbook leaves contain ten leaves of contact prints made by Lynes and/or PAJAMA (the name given to the collective of Paul Cadmus, Jared French and Margaret French). Most of these pages are labeled and seem to have been taken during the summer of 1941. They feature: Mrs. Lawrence Lowman and Lynes; Paul Cadmus, Lynes and Margaret French on Fire Island; Katharine Anne Porter in Saratoga Springs; Barbara and Lloyd Wescott; Jared French and Monroe Wheeler; Glenway Wescott; Adelaide Sparkman Lynes (Lynes' mother); and Somerset Maugham. The remaining loose pages feature a hodge-podge of images similar to the first two volumes. However, one other page was covered with photographic prints. This group has been identified as friends of Max Ewing posing in his apartment in front of his backdrop of Venice. [This "Carnival of Venice" motif is apparent in Ewing's own photograph albums which are also held by the Beinecke Library]. Among the noted names in this group are: Muriel Draper, Paul Robeson, and Lincoln Kirstein.
Series I, Scrapbooks, contains original leaves. Series II, Separated Items, contains items removed from deteriorating leaves for treatment and deacidification. The listing contains information, following the description, which records the original placement of each item in the volumes. SI indicates Scrapbook Volume I; SII - Scrapbook Volume II; SIII - Scrapbook Volume III. For example, the designation "SII-13" means the item originally was attached to page 13 of Scrapbook Volume II. In cases where multiple items were removed from the same page, they have been further annotated with letters to indicate their placement on the original page (e.g. 13a, 13b, 13c, etc.)
Pagination in all three volumes was recorded using different methods due to inconsistent practice on the part of conservators, which was not discovered until all leaves had been deacidified and encapsulated. Volume I is numbered with a single number for each scrapbook leaf - the two sides referred to as "r" for recto and "v" for verso. Volume II is numbered with a single number for each discrete page, as in a printed book. The loose scrapbook leaves were not numbered at all, so page numbers were assigned by the archivist. Pages that were completely blank (with no evidence of having been used) were discarded, though they were counted in the original enumeration of the pages.
Actors; Fashion photography; Gay men -- United States; Photographers -- United States; Photography of the nude; Popular culture -- United States; Photographic prints; Scrapbooks; Lynes, George Platt, 1907-1955; Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1898-1957
- Scrapbooks, ca. 1900-55; Series I; 4.94; (4 boxes)
  - VOLUME I
    - Pages 1-14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      1r: Charles and Ray Eames; Peggy Joyce
      fashion
      1v: GPL with Glenway Wescott, Jean
      Cocteau, and Cecil Beaton; fashion; men
      2r: [Removed item: Colored clipping -
      monkey artist, Viki, with paintings]
      2v: blank
      3-6: blank, discarded
      7r: B. Altman advertisement; [royal
      family?]
      7v: blank
      8-9: blank, discarded
      10r: late 19th century fashion
      10v: blank
      12 loose: Greta Garbo
      12: blank, discarded
      13r: Madame Calve; [removed item:
      Photograph - Painting of two young
      boys reading, marked "Metropolitan
      Museum of Art"]
      13v: Cecile Sorel as Madame du Barry
      14r: Jimmie Pendleton and Mary Denise
      14r: blank
      15-16: blank, discarded
    - Pages 17-21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      17r: [Removed item: Colored clipping -
      African boy in red costume]
      17v: blank
      18r: execution of Vichy militia men by
      Germans
      18v: blank
      19r: unidentified actress in stage
      costumes
      19v: men climbing wooden poles
      20r: explosion near waterfront
      20v: Miss Haidee Wright as Stephanus
      in "The Sign of the Cross"
      21r: Miss "Dickie" Gordon and Duke
      della Verdura at the charity ball of
      the Princess San Faustino; [removed
      item: Colored clippings - Painting by
      Pavel Tchelitchew]; lightning in the
      desert
      21v: blank
    - Pages 22-26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      22r: illustration: "Garden Club"
      (1942); painting of Mrs. Philip Lydig
      by Demeyer; painting of unidentified
      woman (1904)
      22v: drawing of woman by Pavel
      Tchelitchew (1940); movie scene; woman
      on couch
      23r: men with half-submerged airplane
      [removed item: Colored clipping -
      Painting by Pavel Tchelitchew]
      23v-24r: Article on Betty Carstairs
      and Whale Cay, Bahamas
      24v: Soldiers; actresses; Fred and
      Adele Astaire; [removed item: Colored
      clipping - Painting by Marc Chagall]
      25r: men aboard the Dresden
      25v: nude female; Irene Rich
      26r: [Removed item: Colored clipping -
      Photograph of Cecile Sorel]
      26v: [Removed item: Colored clipping -
      Painting by Thomas Eakins]; 2 women
    - Pages 27-30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      27r: man pole-vaulting; Red Cross
      nurse; Abraham Lincoln
      27v: [Removed item: Colored clipping -
      Painting by Bougereau]; Mrs. Patrick
      Campbell; Leonid Massine in Joseph
      Tallulah Bankhead in "No Siree"
      28r: Decor by Tchelitchew for Apollon
      Musagette (1942); building; painting
      of mythical gods and goddesses
      dancer's legs
      28v: Interior of apartment (of GPL?)
      29r: kitten with snake; Pauline Potter
      (de Rothschild)
      29v: [Removed item: Photograph -
      Ambroise Vollard by Brassai]
      unidentified woman
      30r: Gertrude Stein and Alice Toklas
      late 19th century fashion
      unidentified group of people
      30v: blank
      31-35: blank, discarded
    - Loose items before page 36 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
      36loose: Group of loose items
      including: page from "The Sketch"
      (1904 Jun 8); actresses in poses
      drawings by Pavel Tchelitchew
      photographs by GPL from magazines -
      portraits, fashion, ballet, theater
      casts; news photograph of Maud Gonne
      36-38: blank, discarded
    - Page 39 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      39r: Children of the Prince and
      Princess of Wales
      39v: blank
      40-43: blank, discarded
    - Loose items before page 44 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
      44loose: Group of loose items
      including: candid shots of men and
      women; Furuhashi; building and
      monuments; cityscapes; fashion
      paintings by Pavel Tchelitchew
      painting by Florine Stettheimer; pages
      from The Sketch (1903-1904), Theatre Magazine 1926), and View.
  - VOLUME II
    - Remnants of pages 11-12, 71-74 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Pages 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      1: Photographs by Octavius Hill
      Alexandra, Princess of Wales; Norman,
      Chief of MacLeod; [removed items:
      Photographs - Boys playing baseball in
      urban lot and Unidentified man]
      2: [removed items: Photograph - Rear
      view of woman wearing open
      undergarments; Photograph - Melka from
      the Folies Bergères; Colored
      postcard - Nuestra Senora de
      Covadonga, addressed to GPL from Max
      [Ewing?], 1933 Dec 16; Colored
      postcard - "Scénes et types -
      jeune mauresque"; Colored postcard -
      "Casablanca - jeune mauresque rêvant"
      Colored postcard - "Scénes et types -
      jeune Bédouine";]; Greek
      soldier; Natalie Paley; Paul Poiret
      3: Steichen photograph; [Salvador Dali
      and Gala?], painting by Firmin-Girard
      [removed item: Photograph - cabinet
      card, Offenbach by Carjat]
      4: Statue by Gaston Lachaise; "Mae
      West" installation by Dali; cartoon of
      Picasso and Strawinsky; Allen Porter
      and John McAndrew; Jean Cocteau
      [removed item: Colored clipping:
      Photograph of Max Baer by
      Breuhl-Bourges, Vanity Fair, 1934
      Sep]; Pavel Tchelitchew; Lyda Roberti
      5: Garden; mythic scene; painting
      after David Roberts; Coco Chanel
      Gertrude Lawrence
      6: Paul Cadmus with self-portrait
      interior of hall with deer horns; Rex
      Ingram; Baron de Meyer, unidentified
      woman
      7: Photographs by: Beaton,
      Hoyningen-Huene; advertisement by
      Schiaparelli, horse-drawn carriage in
      Paris; [Anna May Wong?], fashion,
      Edward VII
      8: Jean Cocteau; Olympic athletes
      [removed item: Photograph - Group of
      young men in bathhouse or grotto]
      9: Parade in Hyde Park; fashion; Andre
      Gide
      10: "La Mort de L'Amour" (elephants)
    - Pages 11-20 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      11: [Removed items: Photographs - Two
      different prints of Oriental men in
      military or ceremonial costumes
      Photograph - Nude woman posed in front
      of theatrical backdrop holding dagger
      Photograph - Bearded man in workshop]
      12: [Removed items: Photographs -
      Three sheets with multiple poses of
      nude young men and a nude woman with
      a child; Photographs - Four sheets
      with multiple poses of semi-nude
      muscular men (the Ritter brothers)]
      13: [removed items: Photographic
      postcard - Offenbach by Nadar
      Photographic postcard - Gertrude Stein
      and Alice Toklas with Ford truck in
      Rivesaltes, France in front of
      birthplace of Marshall Joffre
      (1917 Apr); Photographic postcard -
      Corot by Nadar, addressed to Miss F. M.
      Cottenet; Photographic postcard -
      Margarete Preuse-Matzenauer addressed
      to GPL by Tonio [Selwart?], [1932
      Apr 19?]; Postcard - Lois Moran,
      addressed to GPL by Max [Ewing?],
      1933 Aug 2; Postcard - Tinted image of
      young man holding flowers
      Photographic postcard: Feral Bengal,
      Folies Bergères; Postcard - "Maroc
      Scénes et types - Marocain préparant
      le thé"; Photographic postcard - Feral
      Bengal, Folies Bergère]
      14: Isadora Duncan with Essenine and
      Irma; [removed items: Photograph -
      Unidentified woman in fur hat and
      coat; Photograph - Unidentified man in
      fur hat and coat; Photograph - Nude
      young man posing under tropical
      plant]; Queen Alexandria and Edward
      VII; Edward Weston
      15: Louis Armstrong; [removed item:
      Photograph - George Sand]; Gloria
      Swanson; International Assemblage of
      Monarchs in 1903
      16: Baudelaire by Nadar; Fritz
      Kreisler; Le Duc de Morny by Nadar
      16loose: Painting by Tchelitchew
      Scene from a play; clipping of
      photograph by Rudolph Burckhardt
      17: Sinclair Lewis; Anna Held; Otto H.
      Kahn; fashion; [removed items:
      Photographs: Two different shots of
      women in traditional Chinese costumes]
      18: Composite photograph of Marlene
      Dietrich and Greta Garbo; fashion
      19: Pablo Picasso; [Ala Nazimova?]
      fashion; Diana Vreeland
      20: Comte Boni de Castellane
      "Thatched Peasants"; [remnants of
      previously removed item]
    - Pages 21-30 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      21: "La Pudeur en Australie"; Jimmy
      Savo
      22: Mahatma Gandhi; fashion; Princess
      Karam of Kapurthala; man with baby
      23: Bill Robinson; Jeanne Engels
      Reuben Sassoon, Hiram Sherman
      [removed items: Photographic postcard
      - Two dance pupils in the Zurich
      Theater, addressed to GPL from
      [Lenjoi?]; Colored clipping: Jimmy
      Daniels with dancers]
      24: Cecil Beaton; English royal
      children in 1912; Mongolian fighters
      King Alfons XIII and Queen Victoria
      Eugenia; [Jean Muir?]
      25: Sir James and Lady Frazier
      fashion; Cecile Sorel; [removed item:
      Photograph - Two oriental men posing
      in simple clothing]
      26: Imogene Coca; [removed item:
      Photograph - Woman posing with
      bracelets and shawl]; woman in shower
      stall
      27: Fashion; visitors to Dali show at
      Julian Levy Gallery; [removed item:
      Photograph - Nude female with fan]
      painting of Constance Askew by
      Pavel Tchelitchew; Mr. and Mrs. Allan
      A. Ryan, Jr.
      28: Trompe-l'oeil interior; Trixie
      Fraganza; Zasu Pitts by Horst
      aboriginal male; fashion
      29: Unidentified men; wheelbarrow
      race; Christian Berard by Beaton
      Josephine Baker; Mary Taylor
      30: Animals wrapped in cellophane
      decapitated head and lynched bodies
      Eleanor Parker
    - Pages 31-40 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      31: Spanish dancers; Empress Charlotte
      of Mexico; Alexandre Dumas with Adah
      Isaacs Menken; men jumping into water
      [removed item: Photographic postcard -
      Head of a burro]; Scene inside Queen
      Victoria's Carriage...
      32: Johnny Weismuller; fashion,
      [removed items: Photographs - Johnny
      Weismuller in four poses: one as
      Tarzan and three aboard a sailboat]
      33: [Removed items: Photographs - Two
      poses of man and woman in fur hats
      and coats]; Emile Zola; Colette
      Baronin Helene Nostiz; Barbette; group
      of young men
      34: Gary Cooper; unidentified men
      Carmel Snow; group of ballet dancers
      men skiing in the nude
      35: Fashion shots by Beaton and
      Hoyningen-Huene; nude men and nude
      woman; Aubrey Beardsley
      36: [Remnants of previously removed
      items]
      37: [Remnants of previously removed
      item]; "A ballroom in the depths of a
      salt mine"; painting of "Jane Austen's
      England"; Robert Shaw; man on
      examining table; Oscar Wilde and
      Alfred Douglas
      38: Fashion; [removed item:
      Photograph - Nude young girl posing
      with tambourine painted with portrait
      of a young man]
      39: Unidentified man at typewriter
      Rodin with wife; Edward Steichen
      self-portrait; Constantin Brancusi
      Coco Chanel by Berenice Abbott; Jean
      Muir by Steichen
      40: Painting by Paul Cadmus, "Two
      Heads"; Katharine Cornell
      unidentified man; men getting dressed
      Mary Taylor
    - Pages 41-50 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      41: Madame Jean Lareviere by Horst
      group of women in field; Mistinguett
      Royal family; Juno's Barge; Queen Mary
      42: Elephant; Alexandra, Princess of
      Wales and Edward, Prince of Wales
      two men; group of acrobats; Anna Sten
      43: Natalie Paley; Thomas Mann; Gregor
      Piatigorsky; women in the Bois de
      Boulogne
      44: Dancers; Henri Desire Landru
      Pablo Picasso; [removed item:
      Photograph - Sheet with multiple shots
      of young women in various poses, by
      Nadar]
      45: Print of group of army men; group
      of men showering
      46: Advertisement for Burdock Blood
      Bitters; Mrs. W. Desmond Humphreys,
      "Rita"; [remnants of previously
      removed items]; Antoine
      47: Ruth Gordon; Peter Lorre
      48: Marlene Deitrich [removed items:
      Photographs: Two different face shots
      of Marlene Dietrich]
      49: John Hay and Liz Whitney; Jeanne
      Eagles; Baobab tree; [removed items:
      Photographic postcard - Two male
      athletes: "Partnerubung: Waage" by
      Siegfried Dietrich; Photographic
      postcard, colored: nude woman on
      chairs by window; Postcard - Mary
      Pickford in "Tess of the Storm
      Country", addressed to GPL by Max
      [Ewing?], 1933 Sep 5; Postcard -
      "Scénes et types: Fatma dans sa
      intérieur; Postcard - "Riatia sous
      la douche"]
      50: Geishas; Lotte Lehman; The
      Marionettes of Mulberry Street"
      aboriginal men; pigs
    - Pages 51-62 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      51: Sculptures by Gaston Lachaise
      cartoon re: social life
      52: Group of clowns; fashion shot
      by Beaton; scene from film: "Man,
      Woman and Marriage"; Miss Alden by
      Nadar
      53: Fashion; "L'énigme du Quai des
      Orfèvres"; Richard Strauss
      54: Dog; bicycle race
      55: Zeppelin burning; burned man
      murderer
      56: Fashion; decapitated heads
      Model wearing large hat - with
      butterfly pasted on image]
      57: Fashion
      58: [Removed items: Photograph - Nude
      young black woman; Photographs - Four
      candid shots of men playing water
      polo]
      59: [Removed items: Photographs -
      Three candid shots of men playing
      water polo]; woman in Welsh costume
      60: [Removed item: Colored clippings -
      "Plaisances et Rocailles par Jean
      Hugo"]; nude girl
      61: [Removed item: Colored clippings -
      Hugo"]; Franz Liszt; Allan Porter
      62: Marcel Proust; Leo Tolstoy and
      wife; painting, "In the Morning Sun"
      by Henry S. Tuke; [removed item:
      Colored clipping: fashion shot with
      woman admiring herself in handheld
      mirror, in front of backdrop by Pavel
      Tchelitchew]
    - Pages 63-76 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      63: Paintings by Tissot; Prince de
      Sagan by Nadar
      64: Performers in underclothes
      Duchess of Marlborough; [removed
      items: Photographs - Three separate
      portraits of unidentified man]
      65 loose: Photographic postcards: Two
      views of matadors in action, one
      identified as "Armillita"
      65: Baron Nicolas de Gunzburg by
      Horst; [removed items: Photographic
      postcards - Three views of matadors,
      two identified as "Serna" and
      "Ortega"]; group of Yale crew members
      group of people conducting a seance
      Grand Duchess Marie of Russia
      66: Elinor Glyn; Gloria Swanson
      tightrope walker
      67: Men in Basque costumes; Carrie
      Daumery; man in native dress [North
      African?]; group of lifeguards
      skiers; statue of Rupert Brooke
      68: "CCC Boy" by Victor Palma; pair of
      male divers
      69: Man in athletic poses; Cleo de
      Merode; [removed item: Colored
      clipping - Fashion illustration by
      Vertes]